Hello and welcome to another episode
with ItsDrdan and this time we're going
to be looking at intermolecular forces.
So when we're looking at intermolecular
forces the big thing here is that
we're trying to understand how
molecules can interact with each
other without creating actual bonds.
So something like water, for example,
when you have a glass of water, all
these individual molecules that are
in here, they're all water molecules.
So H2O, but what are they all doing?
Are they just kind of like all
sitting there, just all wandering
around or are they interacting?
And this is where
intermolecular forces comes in.
So the whole idea behind this, the
word inter is referring to between
molecules and it all feeds off of
the concept of Dipoles, uh, from the,
from previous videos and polarity.
So if I have two dipoles or
two similar molecules, they can
interact with each other like
magnets attracted to one another.
So if you ever take two magnets,
very opposite charges, they
attract, they're going to bring
each other closer as a result.
So these are attracting each other.
However, they are not bonding because
they are not sharing electrons.
So going back to something like our
little water analogy, if I take a
water molecule, so I have a Lewis
structure for water, and I label that
with my delta pluses, delta negatives,
like so, what we're actually going to
see is that Each of these different
positives and negatives can create
an intermolecular force with another
molecule that is of similar quality.
So let's say if I have
another water that is nearby.
And for this one, we
also have the same ideas.
We have the positive and
negative charges here.
Well, I have negative,
positive, negative, positive.
So we have...
An intermolecular force, or
IMF, so we have attraction.
So whenever we have that attraction,
well, that is what we're looking for.
So what types can we have?
Let's look at how we can
really tell the difference.
So there's four major types.
So they are called dispersion,
Dipole dipole, hydrogen
bonding, and ion dipole forces.
So one thing you might see that there is
a lot of in this one is the word dipole.
So you see it once, twice, three
times, um, and so what that's kind of
telling you is that Oh, so two out of
the four have the word dipole in it.
That must be a major
characteristic of these.
So they're all about the polarity that
we've talked about in previous videos.
So if you weren't sure about
electronegativity and polarity, go back
to my last two videos, my other two videos
that were posted previously on them.
I have two parts so far on that.
Hopefully it will help kind of clear
that up before we talk about how
they're attracted to one another.
So let's go through them,
and how let's label them.
So the first one, so dispersion.
Dispersion is a force that
occurs between all molecules.
Okay, so dispersion forces
occur between all molecules.
So it's anything with electrons.
Now, even though it's all
molecules, it's the strongest
force for non polar molecules.
All right, so whenever we have a non
polar molecule, that's all it's capable
of doing so that's whenever you see
something nonpolar and you could label it.
You know, it's only force
is this so what's happening?
So let's say if I take one of the
simplest nonpolar Elements out there
and that would be like a noble gas.
So what if I take a helium now?
How many electrons does
a helium have around it?
Well, if you had remember it goes hydrogen
then helium so it has two electrons.
So if I have those two electrons that
are around it, how exactly is that going
to be kind of displayed around its core?
Well, probability dictates it
should be in as far away from
each other as possible, right?
Like charges repel.
However, what if We have a helium
that collides with another helium.
Being that helium is a gas,
collisions happen all the time.
Um, how exactly would that
occur if they collide?
Well, if that were to happen,
that picture is going...
to change.
So whenever we have a collision,
or it's the same way as if you were
kind of running and someone cut in
front of you and you had to stop, or
let's say if you had to slam on the
brakes of your car, what's to happen?
Well, you jut forward in that seatbelt
and you feel that momentum shift.
So being that electrons are
really, really light, they're
going to fly forward as a result.
So we have a concentration of
electrons on one side of the atom.
Same thing with the other one, right?
Because they collided with each other, all
of a sudden, those electrons in the first
one repelled the ones in the other one.
So when that happened, it caused
a temporary dipole to form.
So we have a positive section,
negative, positive, negative.
So we have temporary Instantaneous dipole.
Instantaneous.
Hopefully I spelled that right.
Okay, so when that happens we have a
brief moment of attraction between these
and it's an extremely weak Interaction.
Okay, so that's the first one.
It's with nonpolar.
Now, what are the trends
with it in terms of strength?
So this is with all molecules and but for
nonpolar, this is the strongest so the
way that it grows in strength strength
increases as molar mass Increases so the
bigger the molecule the more electrons
the stronger the dispersion forces.
So that's stronger dispersion.
That is our first force.
Let's go into our second one.
Our second one was dipole dipole.
Alright, so what was
something with a dipole?
Well, that was whenever we had a
molecule that was, that had a partial
positive and a partial negative charge.
So let's draw a molecule
that would show that.
So what if I had a C double
bonded to an O with two hydrogens?
on both sides.
So for this one, we can try
figuring out the electronegativity.
But if you remember from previously,
one of our trends was that a CO bond is
polar, meaning that the oxygen on this
one is going to be slightly negative.
So we'll have a delta
negative on this side.
Delta plus on that now if this isn't
a similar solution of let's say other
formaldehyde So other, uh, CH2O So how
would they be attracted to each other?
Well, very similar to dispersion being
that these have permanent dive holes
We can kind of maybe imagine that these
are all going to be about how they
can kind of rotate in on themselves.
So I take this molecule, and I rotate it.
So that way the positive side is
exposed, maybe the negative side.
And we bring it closer to,
let's say, another CH2.
Well, we're going to see
that we have a delta plus.
Sorry, delta negative, delta plus.
And we can re label
the other side as well.
So we have negative plus negative
plus, so they are going to make an
intermolecular force between each other.
So this is our dipole dipole, and
this is between polar molecules.
So it has to be polar as a result.
So keep that in mind if we have
something that's polar, then we know
that it is going to be attracted.
So that is dipole dipole.
The next type of force is
whenever we have hydrogen bonding.
So it has to be another
very specific definition.
For this one, hydrogen bonding
is a subtype of dipole dipole.
Hydrogen bonding has to fit the
definition where it has to look like this.
We have to have Let's say an
atom X connected to a hydrogen.
So that's where this part comes into play.
And that thing is going to be interacting.
So that is where the bonding part
comes in with something that is.
Electronegative.
Okay, so in this instance X has to be
a very specific Electronegative atom it
has to be something that's a very very
negative So if you remember from our
electronegativity trends the farther
you were up into the right of the
periodic table The more electronegative
something was so something like fluorine
nitrogen Oxygen have to be one of our
atoms, so it can only be, hydrogen
can only be attached to fluorine,
nitrogen, or oxygen, nothing else.
So when we drew water earlier,
hydrogen bonding, we just didn't
give it a name, so water, hydrogen
bonding to another water molecule.
We showed an instance of hydrogen bonding.
So, oxygen interacts with the hydrogen,
and we have something like this.
And we can label the
different charges, right?
We have minus, plus, minus, plus,
but this shows hydrogen bonding,
because this fits our definition.
Our definition in this instance is
an oxygen is bound to a hydrogen,
And that's interacting with
another oxygen in this situation.
So another example of hydrogen
bonding would be like if I take,
okay, so if it has to be fluorine
or in hydrogen, what if I do HF and
that was interacting with another HF?
So in this case we have
delta plus, delta minus.
That's going to be
interacting with another HF
and we can label them as positive
and minus and we can also show
an instance of hydrogen bonding.
Now, with hydrogen bonding,
there's a little more nomenclature
or naming that comes into this.
So there's the hydrogen bond donor and
there's also the hydrogen bond acceptor.
The donor, so the hydrogen bond
donor, contains the hydrogen.
So in this case, the hydrogen
bond donor is this molecule here
because the hydrogen is interacting.
Whereas on the left over here,
this is the hydrogen bond acceptor,
being that the delta negative.
molecule, or delta negative
atom, in this case fluorine,
is receiving the hydrogen bond.
So it's a further naming system, alright?
The last type of
interaction is ion dipole.
So you might be able to get
an idea of what ion dipole is.
So the first part of the name, an ion.
So you need something with a real charge.
So one example of something with a
real charge is, let's say if I take
Uh, sodium and chlorine, for example.
So if you add salt to
water, what's happening?
If you add sodium, if you add salt
to, let's say, water for making pasta
or making rice, what happens to it?
It all of a sudden dissolves
in front of your own eyes.
Why is that?
Well, that's because of
ion dipole interactions.
So if the water, which has a dipole
on it, were to interact with sodium,
how would that orient itself?
Well, the water would be the oxygen
side, which has the partial negative.
is going to be interacting with
the positive part of the sodium.
And we can draw a bunch of waters
all around that sodium interacting.
So when that happens, those
interactions are gonna surround
that part of that atom there.
And the same thing is going to happen
on the other side, but instead,
or if we have our chlorine, how
is that one going to interact?
Well, being that it's a partial
negative, is it going to be the oxygen,
or the hydrogen is going to interact?
And you might be able to take a guess, is
that the hydrogen, in this case, is going
to interact with the other side because
hydrogen has the slightly positive side.
So when that happens, we're going to be
putting little positive hydrogens all
around that fluorine ion to show how it's
being solvated, or dissolved in this case.
So we have all those little
interactions on all sides.
And that is how we can show interactions
between all these different species.
So the H's, O's, H's, they're all
going to be surrounding it, almost
like a flower kind of surrounding it.
It's actually pretty cool.
So, that is ion dipole forces.
So this is how attractions
occur between molecules.
And one thing you're going to be
seeing is that like molecules, like
to interact with like molecules.
So the last thing I'm gonna leave you
with is our final saying from polar,
from intermolecular forces, and this
is about solubility, is that like
dissolves like, meaning that polar
molecules dissolve polar molecules,
and then non polar Dissolves nonpolar.
So, similar molecules like
to interact with each other.
So, remember that for future videos,
and for to maybe help you with any
homework that you might have, is that
when you're trying to figure out what's
going to be interacting with each
other, it's going to be all about like
dissolves like when you're looking
at all the different types of forces.
I hope this video helped you at least
be able to understand the basics for
trying to understand intermolecular
forces, um, and hopefully we'll see
you next time for future videos.
Please hit that like and subscribe button
so you see future content and I'll keep on
making it for all of you guys out there.
I'll see y'all later.
Bye.